Guide to the Marjorie Heins Papers TAM.805
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Marjorie Heins Papers
1968-2019
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Heins, Marjorie
TAM.805
5.5 Linear Feet in 10 manuscript boxes and 1 media box
7 VHS
8 audiocassettes
5 audiocassettes
5.21 Gigabytes in 154 computer files
Marjorie Heins (1946 - ) is a writer, a former civil rights and civil liberties attorney, and the past director of the Free Expression Policy Project (FEPP) and the American Civil Liberties Union's Arts Censorship Project. Heins has written popular and scholarly articles on free speech, censorship, constitutional law, copyright, and the arts, and has taught at New York University, the University of California - San Diego, Boston College Law School, and the American University of Paris. The Marjorie Heins Papers (dated 1968-2019) consist of materials created and collected by Heins in paper, analog audiovisual, and born-digital format documenting her career as a writer, civil liberties attorney, and founding FEPP director. Materials documenting Heins' research and writing include published articles, subject files, correspondence, reviews, and awards, and predominantly document her books Priests of Democracy: The Supreme Court, Academic Freedom, and the Anti-Communist Purge and Not in Front of the Children: 'Indecency', Censorship, and the Innoncence of Youth. The collection also documents Heins' involvement in the FEPP, including administrative records, research files, interviews, and policy reports on topics such as copyright, fair use, and internet filtering. The collection also includes materials on legal cases and free speech controversies in the 1990s and early 2000s through legal briefs, articles, original writings, and lectures. Audio and video recordings of Heins' public speaking and press appearances are also included in this collection.
Scope and Contents
The Marjorie Heins Papers (dated 1968-2019) consist of materials created and collected by Heins in paper, analog audiovisual, and born-digital format documenting her career as a writer, civil liberties attorney, and founding director of the Free Expression Policy Project (FEPP). Materials documenting Heins' research and writing include published articles, subject files, correspondence, reviews, and awards, and predominantly document her books Priests of Democracy: The Supreme Court, Academic Freedom, and the Anti-Communist Purge and Not in Front of the Children: 'Indecency', Censorship, and the Innoncence of Youth. The collection also documents Heins' involvement in the FEPP through administrative records, research files, interviews, and policy reports on topics such as copyright, fair use, and internet filtering. The collection also includes materials on legal cases and free speech controversies in the 1990s and early 2000s through legal briefs, articles, original writings, and lectures. Audio and video recordings of Heins' public speaking and press appearances are also included in this collection.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Marjorie Heins in June 2021; the accession number associated with this gift is 2021.030.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Biographical Note
Marjorie Heins (1946 - ) is a writer, a former civil rights and civil liberties attorney, and the past director of the Free Expression Policy Project and the American Civil Liberties Union's Arts Censorship Project. Heins has written popular and scholarly articles on free speech, censorship, constitutional law, copyright, and the arts, and has taught at New York University, the University of California - San Diego, Boston College Law School, and the American University of Paris. She is the author of Priests of Our Democracy: The Supreme Court, Academic Freedom, and the Anti-Communist Purge; Not in Front of the Children: Indecency, Censorship, and the Innocence of Youth; Sex, Sin, and Blasphemy: A Guide to America's Censorship Wars; Cutting the Mustard: Affirmative Action and the Nature of Excellence; Strictly Ghetto Property: The Story of Los Siete de la Raza; and Ironies and Complications of Free Speech: News and Commentary from the Free Expression Policy Project, 2001-2017.
Lawyers.; Freedom of speech -- United States.; Civil rights.; Censorship; Heins, Marjorie; Free Expression Policy Project; American Civil Liberties Union
- Heins Articles, 2000-2009 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Heins Articles, 2010-2019 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Heins Papers, Book Chapters, 1997-2011 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Heins Book Review, 1974-2018 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Heins Awards, 1992-2013 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Heins Letters to the Editor, 1992-2002 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Heins Law Review Articles, 1977-2013 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Heins Interviews, 1988-2001 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Heins Articles Quoting, 1985-2004 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1994-2013 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Heins Encyclopedia of NY City -- Correspondence and Research, 2007-2008 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Heins Public Speaking, 2007-2018 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Heins Public Speaking, 2003-2006 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Heins Public Speaking, 2000-2002 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Heins Public Speaking, 1995-1999 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Heins Public Speaking, 1990-1994 (Box 2, Folder 6-7, Box 3, Folder 1-2)
- Video Recordings of Press Appearances, circa 1990s (Box 10, Video 805.001-805.007)
- Audio Recordings of Public Speaking, 1991-2001 (Box 10, Audio 805.008-805.015)
- Priests of Our Democracy -- FBI Shlakman, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Priests of Our Democracy -- Research Notes, Interviews, 2007-2012 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Priests of Our Democracy -- Resource Materials, 2009-2010 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Priests of Our Democracy -- FOIA -- Slochower, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Priests of Our Democracy -- FOIA -- Rapp-Coudert, circa 2010-2013 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Priests of Our Democracy -- Parsons Ph.D. Dissertat, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Priests of Our Democracy -- Justice Frankfurter (Harvard Law SCH Archive), circa 2010-2013 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Priests of Our Democracy -- FBI Ewen, Foner, 2011
  - Digital Files, TW_TAM_805_ER_2 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Paper Files (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Priests of Our Democracy -- Judith Podore Ward, 2011 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Priests of Our Democracy -- Possible Illustrations, 2001-2012 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Priests of Our Democracy -- University of Buffalo Archive, circa 2010-2013 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Priests of Our Democracy -- Reviews and Publicity, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Priests of Our Democracy -- Speaking Gigs, 2013 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Priests of Our Democracy -- Interview Recordings, circa 2010-2013 (Box 10, Audio 805.016-805.020)
- Not in Front of the Children -- Public Speaking, 2001-2002 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Not in Front of the Children -- Reviews, 2001-2005 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Not in Front of the Children -- Library of Congress Research -- Justices' Papers, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Not in Front of the Children -- Research -- Ulysses, 1998-2016 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Not in Front of the Children -- Correspondence, 1999-2001 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Not in Front of the Children -- Library of Congress Research -- Brenna, circa 1998-2005 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Not in Front of the Children -- Illustrations, circa 1998-2005 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Not in Front of the Children -- Public Speaking, 2001-2007 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- ACLU Briefs -- Supreme Court, 1995-2000 (Box 5, Folder 2-4)
- ACLU National -- Briefs, 1994-1997 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- ACLU Arts Censorship Project, 1992-1993 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- ACLU Arts Censorship Project -- Slideshow, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- ACLU Arts Censorship Project --South Africa "Limits of Liberty" Conference, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Massachusetts ACLU Briefs -- Supreme Court, 1981-1987 (Box 5, Folder 9, Box 6, Folder 1-6)
- Massachusetts ACLU -- Annual Reports, 1983-1987 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Massachusetts Attorney General -- Boston Police Report, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Massachusetts Attorney General -- Supreme Court Briefs, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Freedom Expression Policy Project (FEPP) -- Focus Groups and Follow-Up, 2005 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Freedom Expression Policy Project (FEPP) -- Consent Forms for Focus Groups, 2005 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Freedom Expression Policy Project (FEPP) -- Court Brief, 2002-2006 (Box 6, Folder 12, Box 7, Folder 1)
- Freedom Expression Policy Project (FEPP) -- Ironies and Complications of Free Speech, 2017 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Freedom Expression Policy Project (FEPP) -- Reports, Correspondence, Publicity, 2001-2007 (Box 7, Folder 3-6)
- Freedom Expression Policy Project (FEPP) -- AAP Letter, 2001-2002 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Freedom Expression Policy Project (FEPP) -- Briefs -- Supreme Court, 1996-2004 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Freedom Expression Policy Project (FEPP) -- Policy Reports, 2003-2006 (Box 7, Folder 9-10, Box 8, Folder 1)
- Freedom Expression Policy Project (FEPP) -- Public Speaking and Focus Groups, circa 2006-2017; TW_TAM_805_ER_1
- Sex, Sin, and Blasphemy -- Public Speaking, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Sex, Sin, and Blasphemy -- Reviews, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Sex, Sin, and Blasphemy -- New Press, 1993-1995 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- National Campaign for Freedom of Expression, 1997-1998 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Feminists for Free Expression, 1995-1997 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Media Violence -- NYC Bar Association, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Cutting the Mustard, 1988-1989 (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Strictly Ghetto Property, 1973-1992 (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Los Siete de la Raza -- Articles, 1969-1999 (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Heins Other San Francisco Articles, 1968-1973 (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Heins Articles, 1974-1989 (Box 8, Folder 12)
- Heins Articles, 1990-1999 (Box 8, Folder 13)
- Published Books Written by Heins, 1972-2013 (Box 9)